Guide to the Christopher Rhoades Dykema Papers WAG.016
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Christopher Rhoades Dykema Papers
1965-1988
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Dÿkema, Christopher Rhoades, 1944-2008
WAG.016
16.5 Linear Feet (17 boxes)
Christopher R. Dykema was a caseworker for the New York City Department of Social Services, Human Resources Administration and a member of the Social Services Employees Union (SSEU, AFSCME District Council 37, Local 371). While a member of the union, he served as a union delegate and grievance committee chairman, was a participant in contract bargaining (1970-1974), and represented SSEU-Local 371 on the New York City Labor Council (1972-1974). This collection contains material documenting his involvement with various political organizations and unions, and it includes material written by Christopher Dykema for the SSEU and for the New American Movement.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Christopher Dykema in 1981. The accession number associated with this gift is 1981.003. Additional materials were donated in 1989, 1991, 1998 and 2007.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to Series III (boxes 5 through 17) is restricted until the death of the donor and his wife.
Historical/Biographical Note
After graduating from Columbia University in 1966, Christopher Rhoades Dykema began working at the New York City Department of Social Services, Kingsbridge Welfare Center as a caseworker and joined the Social Service Employee Union (SSEU); the union, now SSEU, AFSCME DC 37, Local 371, was then independent. It had been formed when caseworkers split from Local 371 in 1962. He served as an alternate delegate for the union while at Kingsbridge.
Dykema left the Welfare Center for a few years and returned in 1970 to the Bronx Bureau of Child Welfare, where he was active in setting up the Bureau in the union. In the early 1970s, he served as an alternate delegate and delegate from Bronx BCW. He also served as grievance committee chairman and chapter secretary. He participated in contract bargaining (1970-1974) and represented SSEU-Local 371 on the New York City Central Labor Council (1972-1974).
Christopher Dykema was a member of the union during the merger in 1968 of the SSEU and Local 371, and dealt with the aftermath of the reorganization plan set forth after the merger. In the 1969 contract, the union abandoned the caseload limitations and some hiring demands in return for extra money. However, caseloads continued to grow and this collection reflects the caseload problems of the Bureau of Child Welfare. Adding to these problems was the profound effect of the budgetary crisis in New York City in 1975 along with the spiraling inflation of the rest of the decade. This brought about new concerns for the union relating to job security, decline of services to clients, and pay increases based on a weak economy.
During this time, Mr. Dykema was also active in various leftist political organizations, including Students for a Democratic Society (SDS) and the New American Movement (NAM).
Scope and Content Note
Series I: Political Activity, 1966-1988.
Series I includes documents illustrating Dykema's involvement in various leftist political groups including Students for a Democratic Society (SDS) and the New American Movement (NAM). Included in this series are flyers, pamphlets, clippings, and publications from various organizations. Highlights include a pamphlet written by Dykema on socialist organizing in the working class, a paper written by Dykema on the 1975 fiscal crisis in New York City, and SDS and NAM convention material.
Series II: Social Service Employees Union, 1965-1980.
Series II includes minutes, leaflets, notes and papers related to union activities and dissident factions within the local. The series covers union politics, elections, caucuses, negotiations (1970-1974), collective bargaining demands (1971-1974), and grievances (1970-1975). Also included is the SSEU-Local 371 publication Organizational Newsletter(1970-1980). There is a specific focus on the activities of the Bureau of Child Welfare, where Dykema worked. Highlights of this series include a report on the SSEU, written by Dykema, that was presented at a NAM convention.
Arrangement
Arranged alphabetically by topic within each series.
Organized into 2 series:
Missing Title
Series I. Political Activity
Series II: Social Services Employees Union
Pamphlets.; Minutes (administrative records); Newsletters.; Publications (documents); New York (N.Y.); Leaflets (printed works); Civil rights workers |z United States.; Student movements.; White collar workers |x Labor unions |z New York (State) |z New York.; Social Service Employees Union. Local 371; New American Movement (Organization); Red Umbrella (Organization); Padwee, Michael; Students for a Democratic Society (U.S.); Dÿkema, Christopher Rhoades, 1944-2008
- Series I: Political Activity
  - Articles: Leftist Politics, 1968-1988, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Articles: Organized Labor, 1976-1985 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Charma Society, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Columbia University: Leftist Student Organizations, 1968-1970 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Columbia University: Sit-In, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - First Steps: Organizing in the Working Class, by Christopher Dykema, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - July 4th Coalition Demonstration - Philadelphia, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Movement for a Democratic Society (MDS): Newsletter, Dec 1968 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - New American Movement (NAM): Convention Material, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - NAM: Convention Material, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - NAM: Defeat Forced Work and Brownie Points Programs: Testimony Presented by the Metropolitan New York Chapters of NAM, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - NAM: Organizational Material, 1973-1976 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - New York City Fiscal Crisis, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Red Umbrella, 1974 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Scrapbook: Universities and Higher Education, Dec 1968-Apr 1969 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Scrapbook: Universities and Higher Education, May 1969-Sep 1969 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Scrapbook: Universities and Higher Education, Oct 1969 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Students for a Democratic Society (SDS): Organizational Material, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - SDS: Regional Newsletter, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Series II: Social Service Employees Union
  - 10 Downing Street, 1967 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Activists' Lists, 1968-1974 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Activists' Lists, 1975-1980 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Ballots, 1979-1980 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Black Caucus, 1970-1973 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Bureau of Child Welfare Chapter: Organizational Material, 1973-1979 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Caseloads, 1969-1974 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Central Labor Council (NYC), 1974-1976 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - City of New York Department of Social Services, 1967-1973 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - City of New York Department of Welfare, 1967-1973 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - City of New York Human Resources Administration, 1971-1974 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Coalition, 1971-1973 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Cohen, Bart: Caucus, 1972-1973 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Collective Bargaining Demands, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Collective Bargaining Program, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Committee for a New Leadership, 1971-1975 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Committee for a Solid Contract, 1973-1975 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Committees: Minutes, 1967-1979 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Constitution, 1968-1971 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Contract between Local 371 and the City of New York, 1970-1973 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Delegate Assembly Rules Committee, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Department of Social Services: Fiscal Year1975-1976 Budget Request (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - District Council 37, AFL-CIO: Correspondence, 1970-1980 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Elections: Bureau of Child Welfare, 1971-1975 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Elections: District Council 37 Delegates, NYC Central Labor Council Delegate, Trustee of the Welfare Fund and Trustee of Educational Fund, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Elections: General Officers, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Elections: General Officers, 1974, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Evaluation Procedures, 1958-1975 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Executive Committee: Minutes, 1967-1975 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Facts, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Grievances, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Grievances, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Grievances, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Grievances, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - HEW Regulations, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Independent Workers Committee, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Inter-Office Memos: Bureau of Child Welfare, 1970-1975 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Knight Caucus, 1974-1975 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Leaflets, 1966-1968 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Leaflets, 1970-1971 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Leaflets, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Leaflets, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Leaflets, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Leaflets, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Leaflets, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Leaflets, 1976-1980 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Leaflets - Elections, 1970-1973 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Leaflets - Miscellaneous non-SSEU, 1972-1978 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Leaflets - Union Factions, 1970-1975 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Members for a Militant Caucus, 1967-1971 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Militant Workers' Committee, 1971-1973 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Negotiating Committee, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Negotiations, 1970-1971 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Negotiations, 1973-1974 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1966-1968 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Organizational Material, 1968-1980 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Organizational Newsletter, Vol. 7 No. 18, 34, 48-50, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Organizational Newsletter, Vol. 10, No. 1-51, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Organizational Newsletter, Vol. 11, No. 1-51, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Organizational Newsletter, Vol. 12, No. 1-51, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Organizational Newsletter, Vol. 13, No. 1-52, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Organizational Newsletter, Vol. 14, No. 1-52, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Organizational Newsletter, Vol. 15, No. 1-52, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Organizational Newsletter, Vol. 16, No. 1-51, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Organizational Newsletter, Vol. 16, No. 1-50, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Organizational Newsletter, Vol. 17, No. 1-52, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Organizational Newsletter, Vol. 18, No. 1-36, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Political Action News, 1976-1977 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Press Releases, 1965-1966 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Progressive Labor Party, 1971-1978 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Proposal for Child Day Care Centers to Serve the Children of Union Members, Welfare Recipients, and the Local Community, undated (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Proposed Merger Agreement, Social Service Employees Union, Local 371, AFSCME, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Rank and File Committee, 1967-1972 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Report on Legislative / Political Activities, 1977-1978 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Report on SSEU Local 371, by Christopher Dykema, [1972?] (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Service Committee, 1971-1972 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - SSEU Committee to Move the Lists, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Sperling, Jorge: Caucus, 1976-1981 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Union/Management Task Force, 1974-1975 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Unite Slate, undated (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Wavelength, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Welfare Reform Legislation, 1971-1976 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Welfare Workers Committee for Peace in Vietnam, 1967 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Worker Client Alliance, undated (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Workers Action Movement, 1972-1975 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Youth Services Workers: District Council 37, 1975 (Box 4, Folder 19)
- Series III: Unprocessed Materials
  - Unprocessed Materials (RESTRICTED) (Box 5-17)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Access to Series III (boxes 5 through 17) is restricted until the death of the donor and his wife.